<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An elegiacall commemoration of the pious life, and most lamented death, and funerals, of Mr. Josiah Shute, rector of the parish, of St. Mary Woolnoth in Lombard-Street. Who left us on the 13 of June. 1643.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E337</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E75_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21939</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871546</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871546</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123957</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84131)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123957)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 13:E75[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An elegiacall commemoration of the pious life, and most lamented death, and funerals, of Mr. Josiah Shute, rector of the parish, of St. Mary Woolnoth in Lombard-Street. Who left us on the 13 of June. 1643.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Yeare of our Lord, 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouem: 6th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shute, Josias, 1588-1643.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123957:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123957:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ELEGIACALL COMMEMORATION OF THE Pious Life, and moſt lamented Death, and Funerals, of Mr. <hi>JOSIAH SHVTE,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh, of St. MARY WOOLNOTH in Lombard-ſtreet. <hi>Who left us on the 13 of</hi> June. 1643.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Yeare of our Lord, 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:123957:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123957:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Here adventure to offer thee ſome Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Sheets, privately conſecrated to the happy memory of that late Reverend Divine, Mr. JOSIAH SHUTE; by one who had long ſtudied him. They come to thy hands now thus openly, to vindicate the Subject and the Pen which lamented Him: To both which, Malice, or Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or Negligence, or all of them, have done a ſpreading Injury, by ſcattering ſome corrupted Copies; which are ſo ſtudiouſly falſe, that no Line or Sentence carries its firſt and native ſenſe with it. It is but Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon therefore, that the faulty Preſſe, which hath made every Page a continued Errata, ſhould redeeme the multiplyed wrongs it hath done, and recant thoſe falſities which mingle themſelves almoſt in every word and Comma, by ſending abroad theſe more
<pb facs="tcp:123957:3"/> legitimate Leaves; which may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to thee, rather for the Ingenuity and Truth, then the Elegancy or Art which furniſh them. And though the Hand that drew thoſe Lines, drawes it ſelfe in, either thinking that it hath not dreſſed them fine enough to look abroad, or unwilling to ſin among the common Scriblers of the Times; yet certainly it is pardonable in me thus to doe Him right; and to preſent thee with this, though without his leave.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:123957:3"/>
            <head>AN <hi>Elegiacall Commemoration,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Arewell to my Teares! I'le weepe no more. Let thoſe that can finde no other expreſſion for their griefes, then what their ſhewring eyes afford them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile our departed Prophet in the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent language of a Teare; and weepe out Elegies for their ſouls great loſſe: Whileſt I find out ſome other meanes to empty my full Boſome: not that I would willingly part with the remembrance of our <hi>Joſiah,</hi> nor powre out all thoſe ſad thoughts his Death hath left there; (for even my Melancholy is welcome to me, whileſt he is the Subject of it.) But that I would tranſcribe ſome reverentiall conceits, which my contemplative Griefe hath written on my Heart, that may perhaps be better read on my Paper: For, within me, they now have a confuſed Method; and take up ſo much of me, that they ſcarce leave roome for other thoughts, which theſe Times, fruitfull in ſorrowes, do continually dictate to me.</p>
            <p>I may freely admire Thee now; for, thy modeſt Eares are deafe to our applauſe; and thy well-led-life was above our Flattery: So that I ſhall have no cauſe to check my ſelfe, whileſt with praiſe and wonder I runne over the variety of thy merit. Nor ſhall our inquiry begin at the laſt Act of thy Life; we will curſorily, at leaſt, examine every Scene of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:123957:4"/> it; and wil look back upon thee even from thy Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to thy Grave.</p>
            <p>And we ſhall finde Thee conſecrated even from thy Infancy, to the ſervice of thy Great Maſter. Thou wert the Sonne of a Prophet, of a religious and faithfull Miniſter, who was bleſſed with five more; every one of which, with a carefull and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Hand, he led through all their Studies, till He brought them from the Schoole to the Pulpit: and when, as in an eminent Candleſtick, He had there placed them, as ſo many burning &amp; ſhining Lights, (as if there wanted nothing to make Him perfectly happy but Heaven it ſelfe,) He left this world (en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to Him for thoſe five happie Legacies) in a full old age. We will not here any further ſearch after the religious courſes of thy learned Brothers: yet, whileſt we bemoane Thee, we cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the conſiderable loſſe of thy Neighbour<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Shute</hi> of the Poultry, Dr. <hi>Bolſworth</hi> at the Funeral recounted above 3000 Sermons which he had preached.</note> Brother (who was Sainted ſome few yeares before Thee;) whoſe various Learning, whoſe devout In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie, whoſe divine Gifts, made his Life alſo admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and his Death lamented by all that heard of him; being Brother as well to thy Deſert, as Blood.</p>
            <p>When we take a view of Thee, and examine all thy Merit; we need no other deſcription of an exact Proteſtant, and a true Father of the Church. And let thoſe that ſhall hereafter have occaſion to write ſuch a Character, remember Reverend <hi>Shute,</hi> and make Him their Patterne.</p>
            <p>We will firſt conſider Him as a Man; How well He did inſtruct Himſelfe, and preach to his owne ſoule. And we ſhall here find that his ordinary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:123957:4"/> was a continued Lecture. Hee was of<note place="margin">Bene vixit or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinabiliter ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi: ſociabiliter Proximo, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militer Deo. Bernard.</note> a diſpoſition ſociable; yet affording Nature on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch refreſhments as might enable Her, to aſſiſt Him in his holy imployment; for they were but as ſo many preparatives to ſtudy. To all Hee was generally affable, to none ſevere; never diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering any Auſterity, but againſt a confident Sinner. Hee was knowne almoſt to all; acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with but a few. He kept a civill correſpondence with many learned men; but thoſe that He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly beſtowed his leizure houres with; He choſe rather for their free and innocent friendlineſſe, then for any eminencie of their parts; rather ſtudying Books then Men, yet converſing ſo much with the laſt, that He might not be quite a ſtranger to the<note place="margin">His Rectory being worth about 80 li. <hi>Per Annum.</hi>
               </note> times He lived in. His greateſt wealth was the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of content. His greateſt expence next to his Bookes was his Charity, and Hee could never find himſelf touched with any thing like Covetouſneſſe; but when his ſmall Treaſury could not afford Him reliefe for ſome that were the objects of his Pity. He was long happy in a grave and vertuous wife, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was indeed a Father; though He often ſhewed himſelfe ſo to thoſe that were Fatherleſſe. He knew not how to be proud, and could as ill endure a cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Flattery. In briefe, He was a man of ſo even a ſpirit, ſo happily tempered, that He was Maſter of his Paſſions, and had no unruly Humour predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in Him. I could lay downe out of the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his life ſo many divine, ſo many morall rules and precepts; that his very example were direction
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:123957:5"/> enough, how we ſhould ſteere our Actions and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. But theſe are the ſleighteſt pieces of his worth: Let us look upon Him in his proper ſphere, and enquire how fit a man Hee was for his ſacred Function: How he was qualified to be an Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor from the Court of Heaven: and here He will be well worth our wonder: for it will appeare, that all thoſe Eminencies, which doe diſperce and divide themſelves amongſt ſeverall other men did all meet in Him: what was it that any one Man might boaſt of; of his profeſſion which Hee himſelfe was not Maſter of?</p>
            <p>When He ſhewed Himſelfe in his Pulpit, his gravity &amp; preaching countenance, did chaſtize every careleſſe or wanton Hearer: So that to wear his Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture near our Eye or Heart, or to ſuppoſe Him loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon Us were enough, methinks, to fright a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a ſinfull Thought: Devotion hovered about Him; when He was addreſſing Himſelfe to pray; and his whole geſture kindled a warme Zeale even in a frozen Boſome. Whileſt his petitioning words fell from Him; they begate penitent ſighes in thoſe which joyned with Him; to witneſſe that their Hearts breathed out the ſame requeſts: All his Eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations were the ſober dictates of the ſpirit, they were not fiery and ſudden raptures, hudled up, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and born in a haſty minute; his Zeale, though fervent, was modeſtly ordered, conſidering to whom he ſpake: nor did He (on the otherſide) tye himſelf to a few ſet words, as if the Almighty were to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed with ſpels: but his well-fitted Petitions va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried as oft, as any occaſions offered themſelves: and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123957:5"/> when Hee had as it were prepared the attentive Soule by prayer, and begg'd a bleſſing upon His houres diſcourſe; hee ſo chearefully, ſo ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, addreſſed himſelfe to the worke of a holy Orator, that Hee preſently had poſſeſſion of our Eyes, Eares, and Hearts. He ſeldome (unleſſe ſome proper occaſiou call'd for it) varied His Text; or leapt from place to place to ſtart a new Subject; He commonly purſued one piece of Scripture with ſuch learned perſpicuity, ſuch a pious pleaſancy; and did ſo heighten our religious appetites, that we were ſorry for the parting Sands, and long'd for the next houre to finiſh that, which to day perhaps he did only cut out, or divide, for another dayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercize. In His delivery, He was neither affected nor looſe; having ſuch a command of his tongue and voice, that he could handſomely fit them for every ſubject. At a Funerall He pleaded ſo morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyingly in the behalfe of Death; that He made ſome deſirous not to live, others to live better, nor did any returne from Him without a beneficiall convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their owne Mortality. So pathetically would He ſolemnize the paſſion of our Saviour; that his hearers might well laugh at the ſuperſtition of a Crucifix, which only reacheth the gazers eye, or but ſlightly toucheth the abuſed ſoule: when as He imprinted in every heart Chriſt crucified, by repreſenting every circumſtance of His Paſſion ſo to the life, as if He were bleeding a freſh; and were againe ſtabb'd and wounded by us that were His ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Auditory. By theſe meanes He became Maſter of our conſciences, which ſtood in awe of His
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:123957:6"/> words; and were powerfully ſubdued to his ſaving Doctrines. Nor did He adminiſter ſharp things only; He had Balme for the broken and contrite heart; ſoft and gentle perſwaſions to win a tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſoule: He never denounced judgement, but his eyes were big with Teares: He was none of thoſe Thundereres, who repreſent GOD in all his terrible Attributes, and ſhaddow over his Mercy and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. He rather allured then terrified a ſtraying conſcience, and rather endeavoured to bring it home to the Fold, then drive it further from ſafety.</p>
            <p>And though He did dreſſe Divinitie with all the winning advantages, and pious allurements of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Rhetorick: though the words He cloathed it in, were imbroadered with all the flowers of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with golden Sentences, and precious Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (which did cath the attention of every Auditor.) Yet, this Kings Daughter (for ſo is the word, well preached) was all glorious within: the matter, which was the in-ſide, was rich and ſubſtantiall. The weakeſt Capacity went along with Him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandingly, all the way; ſo well did He comply with the meaneſt hearer. The more delicate appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the Nobility and Gentry (which were ſtill part of that Religious Throng) was ſo adviſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuited; that He did, as it were, court them from their ſins, and by a holy Inſinuation, did even ſteale into their Boſomes; and ſo powerfully convince them of their vanities, that they alwayes carried home with them new reſolutions. And the moſt Sober, the moſt Learned Perſons (for ſome ſuch were almoſt alwayes a part of this Auditory) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123957:6"/> in every Sermon ſuch a digeſtion of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Learning, ſo many full expreſſions of a Scholar, of a ſound Preacher, of a Holy man, that they could even have kiſſed the Pulpit, in approbation of thoſe bleſſed Truths ſent down from it.</p>
            <p>There might you ſee the graver Divines, willing to improve their Knowledge and their Piety, by that Summary of Divinitie which might be found in every dayes Lecture. And there might be ſeene the Young-men of the Caſſock (lately ſet up in their Trade for Soules) inabling themſelves for their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Imployment; ſo attentively fixing their whole ſelves on Him, as if they had a deſigne to aſſimilate themſelves to every excellency of His. One eyeing Him, as if he were learning to put on his Reverend Geſture, which gave Life to all that fell from him: the other, how to borrow his unaffected Art, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility of utterance: another, how to weave his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and his meditation with ſuch cunning and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: another, curiouſly obſerving his Method, with a purpoſe to contrive his after labours by ſo rare a Modell. Thus, He was a Preſident for all men; yet was there ſuch a mixture of Grave Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in all theſe Perfections, as if He only had beene ignorant of them.</p>
            <p>And wonder not that this Towre of <hi>David</hi> made ſo faire a ſhew, and had ſo many ſwelling eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, for He had a Foundation large, and ſure. Grace laid the firſt ſtone; and Perſeverance built upon it: a connexion of Piety and Good-works was the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or Ciment: Faith was the Buttreſſe that kept it upright and ſtedfaſt: the Holy Spirit was the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-workman,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123957:7"/> by whoſe active influence every thing was diſpoſed. Nature lent all her aides to make the worke perfect; for, (as ſo many Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, whoſe proper imployments were herein neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary,) ſhe lent an open Capacitie, a retentive Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, a ſearching wit, a trying Judgement: And here were all thoſe ſervants of Art which make the ſuper-ſtructure; as indefatigable Induſtry, inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Studie, curious Obſervation, ſatisfying Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and the uſefull extractions of Bookes and Antiquities.</p>
            <p>Let it then be the boaſt of others, that they are able to performe the moſt ſacred and myſterious office of the Miniſtery, without being much behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Learning, that neceſſary Hand-maide to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Knowledge; whileſt we pitie, and laugh at the cunning Ignorance of theſe zealous Drones. It will be a worthy addition to his laſting Fame, that He was not contented to make himſelfe intimate with the whole Scripture, and have every Text readie to refute an Adverſarie, or convince a Sinner: but He did run over the whole Bodie of Learning, ſipping from every part of it, as from ſo many flowers, ſome ſerviceable notions, which being by his holy Art di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted (as by the ſubtile Chymeſtrie of the Bee) help'd to make up that Honey, thoſe ſweet and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall Lectures, with which He frequently entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned us.</p>
            <p>He read the Bible in that Originall language, in which thoſe happie Secretaries to the Holy Ghoſt penned it; that he might be the more familiar with the true intentions of every word and expreſſion of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:123957:7"/> it; making himſelfe acquainted with the learned Languages, becauſe he would look back into the firſt Eſſence and purity of things, before the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexing variety of humane conceipt had ſpent it ſelf upon it: that he might examine upon what Grounds and Reaſons, the antient Expoſitors and Fathers have founded thoſe numerous Volumes, which at this day do furniſh our holy Libraries. Doing this, not out of a proud curioſitie, or to defend Errour; but out of a reverend feare of aſſenting to the newer opinions of any, how eminent ſoever; if he found them diſſonant to thoſe ancient verities, which he ſtudiouſly traced, by going ſo far backward into the unfoiled Learning and wiſdome which was behinde him.</p>
            <p>And then,—But I'le ſumme up no more of his parts, but, will abruptly leave his many abilities in the mid-way: Seeing every Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of his told us how generally, how admirable he was qualified; for, they were not the elaborate Iſſues of many dayes, (ſo much time not being allowed him) but they were the diſgeſted quinteſſence of his former labours; to which his leiſure only gave him leave to adde little elſe but Meditation, &amp; Method. There is yet ſomething behinde which will give more luſtre to his precious Memory. It is poſſible, that we may finde his parallell, if we only look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the qualifications of Learning and ſtrong Parts. But, where ſhall we finde ſo much ſober integrity; one ſo like to thoſe firſt Diſciples, whoſe immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Tutor, Chriſt himſelfe was? One, that ſo deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly may be ſtiled an Apoſtle of our Church? Herein lay his prime Excellency.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:123957:8"/>
            <p>Let us firſt looke upon Him, as appointed by his great Maſter to the cure of thoſe ſoules, amongſt whom He expired; we ſhall find Him continually diligent in his charge (where He fixed himſelfe for one and thirty years) behaving Himſelfe much like that Shepherd, that gave his life for his ſheepe: for it is well knowne, He ſpent himſelfe ſo without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion in his ſtudy and his Pulpit: that his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirred humours (which wanted part of that immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate exerciſe which his ſpirits had) ſetled into Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes; w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> preſſed upon Him ſo violently in his later years; that he often preached in pain, in faint ſweats, nay, ſometimes in Bloud; of which he had many ſad witneſſes. Nor could He be won from his ſtation, wherein his Conſcience told Him, his God had ſet Him, by any richer Invitations, or Livings of a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<note place="margin">Oſtered Him by ſome of his Lay-friends.</note> value; which he often refuſed, as unwilling, when Hee had brought his neighbours ſoules halfe-way to Heaven, to leave them to a new Convoy; who might perhaps rather direct them a crooked courſe, or bring them back againe, then helpe them forward, (for He would often lament the paucity of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious Guides.) He was obſerved to be ſo far from that (almoſt epidemicall) crime of Temporizing, that he was looked upon as a profeſſed (though not a rigid) Antagoniſt to the times he lived in, as if he ſcorned to bee a Favourite to that predominant Power, under which the evils he lamented, ſeemed to him to receive their countenance and growth; his well-ſetled ſoule was ſtill kept within its religious Center, and could never be conjured out by all thoſe powerfull Charmes which Ambition ſcatters, to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123957:8"/> enveagle the judgements and inclinations of her oppoſites. Yet he ſometimes commanded himſelfe to a mannerly and civill obedience, as a ſubject, and a ſonne of the Church; in ſome indifferent things rather yeelding to the publique, and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, than to the wilfulneſſe of his own private opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. But when at any time he ſaw plainly any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct Deſignes on foot, which ſome great Agents in Church and State, kept going, either to put new fetters upon the ſubjects, or new diſguiſes on Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; he could never be courted to lend his Tongue to make Apologies for their Innovations; nor could be ſilenced from declaiming againſt the dangerous attempts of theſe firſt troublers of Iſrael. And there needs no greater approbation of his uprightneſſe, nor a fuller conviction of the corrupt <hi>Genius</hi> of thoſe dayes, then that he and ſome more of his Form, (whoſe ſtanding in the gap, when ſuperſtition was ruſhing in, drew upon them that then venerable nick name of Puritans) were ſo long left unpreferred; whileſt the Dignities of the Church (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſhold have been the reward of Men, ſingular for their Piety and Ability) were chiefly taken up by ſuch who rather ſtudied, preached, and practiced the Politiques then Divinity. And when afterwards, the winds were quite turned, when ſtormes and foule weather ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to threaten every one that came not into the new roade, he did not forſake that Anchor of a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reſolution, but rather endured ſharpe blaſts of envie and malice; diſdaing a wavering compliance to the fatall alterations of our giddie times; which drew from him many a Tear, &amp; private groan: Nor could he refraine from a more open expreſſion of his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123957:9"/> griefe, though there was danger and ſuſpition in his very Sighs: For he would modeſtly and warily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of, and bewaile the miſcariages or miſtakes of thoſe above him: but with a warme and warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Zeale be angry with ſuch among the heady people, who would not ſee the confuſion they were violently hurrying into. No bold-fac'd ſinne could ſcape him without a ſeaſonable reprehenſion. No diſtructive Doctrines, no falſe gloſſes, no ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Tares could be ſowed by the Malice or Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of any, but he would carefully ſet himſelfe to the weeding of them out betimes; leſt the ſeeds of them ſhould prove fruitfull; and ſcatter themſelves in his well-kept Garden, (for ſuch is a Pariſh well inſtructed.) He was ſo earneſt a Lover of Union and right Devotion that the dividing Separatiſt, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Papiſt received a wound from him at every Lecture. To conclude, hee was ſuch an eager oppoſite to all thoſe things that interrupted our Peace, and ſullied the faire Face of Truth; that we muſt needs complaine, that Truth and Peace have loſt one of their chiefe Champions.</p>
            <p>Nor did he encounter the divers enemies of the times with a loud violence, but moderately and calmely overthrew Them; (having learned the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment of breaking a Flint with more eaſineſſe upon a cuſhion) ſcorning that vain-glory, and thoſe falſe ends, which make ſome partially and uncivilly raile againſt the preſent managers of our Affaires; tempting on purpoſe the Anger and the power of thoſe, whoſe Intereſt commands them to ſtop their their mouthes: that they may undeſervedly gain the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123957:9"/> title of a Prerogative Martyr, and hazard their pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty preferments, in expectation of ſome better guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: ſo catching at a Dignity, by their hot ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they were never likely to reach by their luke-warme Devotion. But his Diviner Soule knew no indirect ends; the Cathedrall honour, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had any magnetick Influence upon his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: his Eye and his Heart were alwayes toward Heaven, as if he thence expected his Biſhoprick; and deſired no other preferment, then what was there laid up for him: Being ſo high minded, that he ſlighted the Miter to make himſefe ſure of a Crowne.</p>
            <p>It is time that I ſhould make haſte to his Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, leſt, when I have enquired after, and call'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether all his worth, my Reader want faith to goe along with me further. Let us therefore deſcend quickly to his declining, and we ſhall finde an eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning becomming ſuch a day, glorious even in his Sun-ſet. Nor could we look for any other Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe at the laſt Scene, when all the reſt of his life was ſo well Acted. He lived 55 yeares to learn how to dye well; for indeed his whole Age was no otherwiſe imployed. At laſt, Nature being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrought, groaned under many Infirmities; which with cheerefulneſſe he a great while paſſed over; till Death, which would not be deferr'd further; and Heaven, which would no longer be without this Gueſt, agreed together to ſummon him, by a ſwouning Fit; which (as ſoone as he had retired out of his Pulpit into his Chamber) ſuſpended his ſpirits and had throwne him on the ground; had not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:123957:10"/> a luckie friend (whoſe fortune it was to cloſe his eyes at laſt) then by chance reſcued him from the Fall. After this, his Diſeaſe purſued him ſo cloſe, that it took him from his profeſſion; and this hee accounted Death even before Death to be forc't from his Pulpit, where he would willingly have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, his ſoule being then nearer, and on its way to heaven.</p>
            <p>But, Bleſſed Man, thou mad'ſt thy Bed thy Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit; and finding thy Soule upon her Wing, thou didſt (almoſt after thy uſuall Method) betake thy ſelfe to thy Text, which was, that commanding Monoſyllable Death. Yet before thou didſt enter upon it, thou didſt prepare thy few and happie Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, by a moſt devout and patheticall Prayer; wherein all the world was beholding to thy exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Charitie. And, may thy bleeding Countrie, thy diſquieted Prince, thy divided Brethren, thy melancholy Friends, and even thy peeviſh enemies feele thoſe Bleſſings, which in thy laſt words thou didſt beg for them. When thou hadſt (as if thou didſt intend them as ſo many Legacies) ſumm'd up all things which are neceſſary for us; Thou didſt bequeath thy ſelfe into thoſe hands that made thee, and ſuddenly after didſt fall aſleepe.</p>
            <p>He that ſhall with a contemplative ſoule obſerve all this, and yet want a Sermon to teach him how to dye well, when Reverend SHUTE now very near a Saint, preacheth from his Death-bed to him, will hardly be brought to a true ſenſe of ſaving Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſhould his bleſſed Angell deſcend, and bring down inſtructions more immediately from GODS
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:123957:10"/> Mouth, how he might dye to live immortallie.</p>
            <p>Nor did this Man of God, goe to his Grave with meane Funerals; he had more true Mourners then followed the Hearſe of a departed Prince. Such put on an affected griefe with their diſſembling blacks; and at theſe ſtately Obſequies there is no circumſtance which is like Sorrow, but a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Solemnitie: when as there wanted no Pageants of Mortality nor borrowed ſadneſſe to attend him to the houſe of Death. In his Melancholy Traine, (which was made up of thouſands beſides his droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kindred) it was hard to finde out a dry eye, or a face wherein griefe did not apparently ſhew it ſelfe. The Nobility and Gentry could not command their Teares; or were willing to beſtow that laſt gatefull ſhowre, in acknowledgement of thoſe many bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings they owed him for. The dejected Clergie hung downe their heads, as if they had loſt the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of their Profeſsion. His ſad Pariſhioners, who for ſo many yeares had received the bread of life by his faithfull Miniſterie, looked pale and diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, as though they had feared a ſucceeding Famine. And the reſt of the weeping croud (who had hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore gathered up, whileſt he ſhook the Tree of Life to all that came) by their Laments and Peales of ſighes did witneſſe, that they had ſoules ſenſible of the injuries which death had done them by taking away him; who alwayes ſtood Sentinell for all his Auditors, and gave them a timely Alarum againſt the ſurprizals of their Arch-Enemy, the Devill.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Vdall</hi> that preached his Funerall Sermon.</note> Well then might his Learned Friend have ſpared his Funerall Lectnre; for there were no eyes preſent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:123957:11"/> which needed pumping, no hearts, which were not already melted, at this Buriall of their Favourite. But his words were Cordiall to us, when he excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently ſhewed; how, <hi>He had fought a good fight, fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Text at his Funerall.</note> 
               <hi>his courſe,</hi> and <hi>kept the faith,</hi> and was gone to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Crowne of Righteouſneſſe which the Lord the righteous Judge had laid up for him.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore wipe our eyes, ſeeing we are ſo well aſſured of his happineſſe, leſt we ſeeme to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie him his bleſſed repoſe, and the reward of his righteouſneſſe, which, we have reaſon to hope is as certaine, as that the Almighty is mercifull; and that he hath prepared heaven for a Kingdome, and immortality for a Crowne, <hi>for all thoſe that have fought a good fight,</hi> &amp;c. Yet, 'tis ſaid, there want not thoſe that dare more then doubt of his ſoules bliſſe. Oh, deſparate uncharitableneſſe, even againſt their own ſelves! If our God be ſo ſevere, that thy well-dreſt ſoule (which never went without its true Wedding-garment) cannot be admitted: what ſhall become of thoſe, who have nothing but rags of vanity, and patches of pretended zeale to cloath their ſinfull nakedneſſe? O my God, if there be no roome in Heaven, for this good, this vigilant Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, where ſhall his poore weak flock be folded, when we are driven out of this life? Is not the Gate of Bleſſedneſſe narrow enough, but muſt wretched man ſtreighten it, yet farther? If ſo much, ſo pure Piety cannot enter; how ſhall prophaneneſſe and accumulated ſin ſtruggle through? That forward Intruder that will make himſelfe of Gods Jurie, and dares preſumptuouſly condemne the Juſt and Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:123957:11"/> paſſeth a ſure ſentence againſt his own ſoule.</p>
            <p>But, Heaven and Earth (whoſe Darling he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes was) have lifted him above the reach of their violent malice. And whileſt God and Men (having now divided him betwixt them) ſhall take care, the one of his Soule, the other of his Fame; and ſhall eternize him in the Regiſter of the Saints; the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of theſe dregs of men, (who are profeſſed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies even to Mortality, to Learning, Vertue, Piety, almoſt to all thoſe true and eſſentiall parts of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Religion) ſhall be odious to Poſterity; (to which they have help'd to give a wound by their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and unlimited zeale and practiſes, which will be beyond the cure either of Time or Policy.) Yet even for theſe Malignant Spirits, his Soule left a bleſſing, whileſt he begd of the Almighty (whither he was about to goe) to enlighten and amend their bloodſhed eyes, and to pardon their wilfull and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious Blindneſſe. Thus, inſtead of repaying the Gall of his Detractors with Bitterneſſe, he tooke them into his Prayers, and ſo ſacrificed for their ſin; a benefit beſtowed upon them againſt their will and merit.</p>
            <p>Come hither then all ye that have any aime at heaven, and ſet your ſelves to ſtudy the life and death of this holy man: what we cannot performe by his precepts, and paſſed Inſtructions; let us reach at by his example and imitation. Thus he may live with us in deſpight of Death: and preach ſaving Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines; though himſelfe be for ever ſilenced. Thus every pious boſome may make it ſelfe his Tombe; which, being adorned with any reſemblance of his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:123957:12"/> better part, will more fully evidence his worth, then a ſpeaking marble, whoſe partiall Inſcrptions doe moſt times flatter their dead gueſts; and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore juſtly ſuſpected, as no more then a Funerall Complement. Yet, it were both pity and ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, ſhould that ſilver Trumpet (which hath ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten awakened us from our ſinfull Lethargies) be be now hudled up in common duſt, without ſome little memoriall, where it is laid up. Go on then; and doe you (whoſe ſoules were above thirty yeates obliged to him,) deliver him over to Poſterity in your intended Monument. That when aged Time hath worne out all thoſe, who have been witneſſes of his matchleſſe parts and Piety; the ſtones may tell his happy ſtory, by offering this Epitaph to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Reader,</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Here lies,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:123957:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
